<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-13T15:08:26+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">A. J. Morris Group</title><subtitle>Universities of Birmingham and Cambridge
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cation Disorder and Lithium Insertion Mechanism of Wadsley–Roth Crystallographic Shear Phases from First Principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/09/13/autogen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cation Disorder and Lithium Insertion Mechanism of Wadsley–Roth Crystallographic Shear Phases from First Principles" /><published>2019-09-13T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-13T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/09/13/autogen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/09/13/autogen.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Publication by Can in the Journal of the American Chemical Society</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/09/13/Can2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Publication by Can in the Journal of the American Chemical Society" /><published>2019-09-13T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-13T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2019/09/13/Can2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/09/13/Can2.html">&lt;p&gt;The prediction of topological preferences and polymorph stability remains a challenge for the design of metal–organic frameworks exhibiting a rich topological landscape, such as zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs). Here, we have used mechanochemical screening and calorimetry to test the ability of dispersion-corrected periodic density functional theory (DFT) to accurately survey the topological landscape, as well as quantitatively evaluate polymorph stability, for a previously not synthesized ZIF composition. Theoretical calculations were used to obtain an energy ranking and evaluate energy differences for a set of hypothetical, topologically distinct structures of a fluorine-substituted ZIF. Calculations were then experimentally validated via mechanochemical screening and calorimetry, which confirmed two out of three theoretically anticipated topologies, including a fluorinated analogue of the popular ZIF-8, while revealing an excellent match between the measured and theoretically calculated energetic differences between them. The results, which speak strongly in favor of the ability of dispersion-corrected periodic DFT to predict the topological landscape of new ZIFs, also reveal the ability to use peripheral substituents on the organic linker to modify the framework thermodynamic stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/jacs.9b06316&quot;&gt;Full Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The prediction of topological preferences and polymorph stability remains a challenge for the design of metal–organic frameworks exhibiting a rich topological landscape, such as zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs). Here, we have used mechanochemical screening and calorimetry to test the ability of dispersion-corrected periodic density functional theory (DFT) to accurately survey the topological landscape, as well as quantitatively evaluate polymorph stability, for a previously not synthesized ZIF composition. Theoretical calculations were used to obtain an energy ranking and evaluate energy differences for a set of hypothetical, topologically distinct structures of a fluorine-substituted ZIF. Calculations were then experimentally validated via mechanochemical screening and calorimetry, which confirmed two out of three theoretically anticipated topologies, including a fluorinated analogue of the popular ZIF-8, while revealing an excellent match between the measured and theoretically calculated energetic differences between them. The results, which speak strongly in favor of the ability of dispersion-corrected periodic DFT to predict the topological landscape of new ZIFs, also reveal the ability to use peripheral substituents on the organic linker to modify the framework thermodynamic stability.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ab Initio Prediction of Metal-Organic Framework Structures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/06/09/autogen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ab Initio Prediction of Metal-Organic Framework Structures" /><published>2019-06-09T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/06/09/autogen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/06/09/autogen.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Wataru Sekine joins the group</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/05/17/Wataru.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Wataru Sekine joins the group" /><published>2019-05-17T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-17T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2019/05/17/Wataru</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/05/17/Wataru.html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wataru Sekine will be joining the Morris group for a year.  He is from the Murata Manufacturing Co. Ltd. in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dr. Wataru Sekine will be joining the Morris group for a year. He is from the Murata Manufacturing Co. Ltd. in Japan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Theoretical Prediction and Experimental Evaluation of Topological Landscape and Thermodynamic Stability of a Fluorinated Zeolitic Imidazolate Framework</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/04/29/autogen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Theoretical Prediction and Experimental Evaluation of Topological Landscape and Thermodynamic Stability of a Fluorinated Zeolitic Imidazolate Framework" /><published>2019-04-29T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-29T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/04/29/autogen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/04/29/autogen.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Publication in Chemistry of Materials on Zeolitic Imidazolate Frameworks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/04/29/ACS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Publication in Chemistry of Materials on  Zeolitic Imidazolate Frameworks" /><published>2019-04-29T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-29T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2019/04/29/ACS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/04/29/ACS.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract&lt;/em&gt;: The prediction of topological preferences and polymorph stability remains a challenge for the design of metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) exhibiting a rich topological landscape, such as zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs). Here, we have used mechanochemical screening and calorimetry to test the ability of dispersion-corrected periodic density functional theory (DFT) to accurately survey the topological landscape, as well as quantitatively evaluate polymorph stability, for a previously not synthesized ZIF composition. Theoretical calculations were used to obtain an energy ranking and evaluate energy differences for a set of hypothetical, topologically-distinct structures of a fluorine-substituted ZIF. Calculations were then experimentally validated via mechanochemical screening and calorimetry which confirmed two out of three theoretically anticipated topologies, including a fluorinated analogue of the popular ZIF-8, while revealing an excellent match between the measured and theoretically calculated energetic difference between them. The results, which speak strongly in favor of ability of dispersion-corrected periodic DFT to predict the topological landscape of new ZIFs, also reveal the ability to use peripheral substituents on the organic linker to modify the framework thermodynamic stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.chemmater.9b00994&quot;&gt;Full Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Abstract: The prediction of topological preferences and polymorph stability remains a challenge for the design of metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) exhibiting a rich topological landscape, such as zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs). Here, we have used mechanochemical screening and calorimetry to test the ability of dispersion-corrected periodic density functional theory (DFT) to accurately survey the topological landscape, as well as quantitatively evaluate polymorph stability, for a previously not synthesized ZIF composition. Theoretical calculations were used to obtain an energy ranking and evaluate energy differences for a set of hypothetical, topologically-distinct structures of a fluorine-substituted ZIF. Calculations were then experimentally validated via mechanochemical screening and calorimetry which confirmed two out of three theoretically anticipated topologies, including a fluorinated analogue of the popular ZIF-8, while revealing an excellent match between the measured and theoretically calculated energetic difference between them. The results, which speak strongly in favor of ability of dispersion-corrected periodic DFT to predict the topological landscape of new ZIFs, also reveal the ability to use peripheral substituents on the organic linker to modify the framework thermodynamic stability.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hypergolic zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs) as next-generation solid fuels: Unlocking the latent energetic behavior of ZIFs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/04/05/autogen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hypergolic zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs) as next-generation solid fuels: Unlocking the latent energetic behavior of ZIFs" /><published>2019-04-05T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-05T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/04/05/autogen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/04/05/autogen.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Publication in Science Advances on the Next Generation of Solid Fuels</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/04/05/Science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Publication in Science Advances on the Next Generation of Solid Fuels" /><published>2019-04-05T01:00:01+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-05T01:00:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2019/04/05/Science</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/04/05/Science.html">&lt;p&gt;This new publication, “Hypergolic zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs) as next-generation solid fuels: Unlocking the latent energetic behavior of ZIFs” higlights novel electronic properties in these materials which were previously unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract&lt;/em&gt;: Hypergolic materials, capable of spontaneous ignition upon contact with an external oxidizer, are of critical importance as fuels and propellants in aerospace applications (e.g., rockets and spacecraft). Currently used hypergolic fuels are highly energetic, toxic, and carcinogenic hydrazine derivatives, inspiring the search for cleaner and safer hypergols. Here, we demonstrate the first strategy to design hypergolic behavior within a metal-organic framework (MOF) platform, by using simple “trigger” functionalities to unlock the latent and generally not recognized energetic properties of zeolitic imidazolate frameworks, a popular class of MOFs. The herein presented six hypergolic MOFs, based on zinc, cobalt, and cadmium, illustrate a uniquely modular platform to develop hypergols free of highly energetic or carcinogenic components, in which varying the metal and linker components enables the modulation of ignition and combustion properties, resulting in excellent hypergolic response evident by ultrashort ignition delays as low as 2 ms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/4/eaav9044&quot;&gt;Full Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This new publication, “Hypergolic zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs) as next-generation solid fuels: Unlocking the latent energetic behavior of ZIFs” higlights novel electronic properties in these materials which were previously unknown.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First CASTEP Users Meeting in Birmingham is a Great Success!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/03/20/CASTEPWorkshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First CASTEP Users Meeting in Birmingham is a Great Success!" /><published>2019-03-20T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-20T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2019/03/20/CASTEPWorkshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2019/03/20/CASTEPWorkshop.html">&lt;p&gt;The first CASTEP Users Meeting was held this week in Birmingham, and organised by Andrew and Phil Hasnip.  The meeting was a success, with speakers travelling from as far as Taiwan to attend the workshop.  At the meeting, one of the Morris group PhD students, Angela Harper, took home the first place poster prize for her work on “Electronic Structure and Properties of Transition Metal Phosphides”.  Featured in the image here is Bjoern Winkler from Goethe University, Frnakfurt, Germany, giving the first talk of the workshop on “Understanding phase transitions using CASTEP”.  Andrew, and the rest of the CASTEP community are looking forward to hosting more workshops such as this one in the coming years, to make this an annual occurance.  This is in addition to the CASTEP Workshop held each year in August for new users and CASTEP developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on CASTEP, and to stay informed about upcoming workshops, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.castep.org/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The first CASTEP Users Meeting was held this week in Birmingham, and organised by Andrew and Phil Hasnip. The meeting was a success, with speakers travelling from as far as Taiwan to attend the workshop. At the meeting, one of the Morris group PhD students, Angela Harper, took home the first place poster prize for her work on “Electronic Structure and Properties of Transition Metal Phosphides”. Featured in the image here is Bjoern Winkler from Goethe University, Frnakfurt, Germany, giving the first talk of the workshop on “Understanding phase transitions using CASTEP”. Andrew, and the rest of the CASTEP community are looking forward to hosting more workshops such as this one in the coming years, to make this an annual occurance. This is in addition to the CASTEP Workshop held each year in August for new users and CASTEP developers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First-Principles Study of Localised and Delocalised Electronic States in Crystallographic Shear Phases of Niobium Oxide</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/02/26/autogen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First-Principles Study of Localised and Delocalised Electronic States in Crystallographic Shear Phases of Niobium Oxide" /><published>2019-02-26T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-26T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/02/26/autogen</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/02/26/autogen.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>